When I was a kid,
عندما كنت طفلاً،
the disaster we worried about most was a nuclear war.
كانت الكارثة التي كنا قلقين بشأنها هي الحرب النووية.
That's why we had a barrel like this down in our basement,
لهذا السبب كان لدينا مثل هذا البرميل في الطابق السفلي،
filled with cans of food and water.
مليء بعلب الطعام والماء.
When the nuclear attack came,
عند حدوث الهجوم النووي،
we were supposed to go downstairs, hunker down, and eat out of that barrel.
من المفترض إلاحتماء في الطابق السفلي، والأكل من محتويات البرميل.
Today the greatest risk of global catastrophe
أما اليوم فأعظم كارثة عالمية
doesn't look like this.
لا تبدو كهذه.
Instead, it looks like this.
بل، تبدو مثل هذا.
If anything kills over 10 million people in the next few decades,
إذا كان أي شيء سيقتل أكثر من 10 ملايين شخص في العقود القليلة القادمة،
it's most likely to be a highly infectious virus
فمن المرجح أن يكون فيروس شديد العدوى
rather than a war.
وليس الحرب.
Not missiles, but microbes.
ليست الصواريخ، ولكن الميكروبات.
Now, part of the reason for this is that
جزء من السبب وراء ذلك هو
we've invested a huge amount in nuclear deterrents.
إستثمارنا لمبالغ ضخمة من أجل الردع النووي
But we've actually invested very little in a system to stop an epidemic.
ولكننا في الواقع لا نستثمر سوى القليل جداً في أيقاف الأوبئة.
We're not ready for the next epidemic.
لسنا على استعداد للوباء القادم.
Let's look at Ebola.
دعونا ننظر الى إيبولا.
I'm sure all of you read about it in the newspaper,
أنا متأكد من أن كل واحد منكم اطلع عليه في الصحف،
lots of tough challenges.
الكثير من التحديات الصعبة.
I followed it carefully through the case analysis tools
تتبعته بعناية من خلال أدوات التحليل
we use to track polio eradication.
المستخدمة لمراقبة القضاء على شلل الأطفال.
And as you look at what went on,
وكما شاهدتم فيما مضى،
the problem wasn't that there was a system that didn't work well enough,
لم تكن المشكلة في أن النظام لا يعمل بشكل جيد بما فيه الكفاية،
the problem was that we didn't have a system at all.
وإنما تكمن في عدم وجود نظام على الإطلاق.
In fact, there's some pretty obvious key missing pieces.
في الواقع، كانت هناك بعض القطع الرئيسية المفقودة.
We didn't have a group of epidemiologists ready to go, who would have gone,
لم يكن لدينا مجموعة من علماء الأوبئة مستعدين للذهاب
seen what the disease was, seen how far it had spread.
لرؤية ما كان هذا المرض، ومعاينة مدى سرعة انتشاره.
The case reports came in on paper.
لقد جاءت تقارير الحالة على ورق.
It was very delayed before they were put online
لقد تأخرت كثيراً قبل وضعها على الانترنت
and they were extremely inaccurate.
ولم تكن دقيقة للغاية.
We didn't have a medical team ready to go.
لم يكن لدينا فريق طبي على استعداد للذهاب.
We didn't have a way of preparing people.
ولم يكن لدينا أي وسيلة لإعداد الناس.
Now, Médecins Sans Frontières did a great job orchestrating volunteers.
لقد قامت منظمة أطباء بلا حدود بعمل عظيم في تنظيم المتطوعين.
But even so, we were far slower than we should have been
ولكن ومع ذلك، مازلنا بعيدين كثيراً عما كان ينبغي
getting the thousands of workers into these countries.
وهو الحصول على الآلاف من العمال في هذه البلدان.
And a large epidemic would require us to have hundreds of thousands of workers.
قد يتطلب وباء كبير أن يكون لدينا مئات الآلاف من العمال.
There was no one there to look at treatment approaches.
لم يكن هناك أحد ليبحث عن أساليب علاجية.
No one to look at the diagnostics.
لا أحد لإلقاء نظرة على التشخيص.
No one to figure out what tools should be used.
لا أحد لمعرفة أي أداة ينبغي أن تستخدم.
As an example, we could have taken the blood of survivors,
وكمثال على ذلك، كان بإمكاننا أخذ الدم من الناجين،
processed it, and put that plasma back in people to protect them.
معالجته، ووضع هذه البلازما مرة أخرى في الناس لحمايتهم.
But that was never tried.
ولكن هذا لم يجرب أبدا.
So there was a lot that was missing.
لذا كانت هناك الكثير من الأشياء الناقصة.
And these things are really a global failure.
وكانت ذلك عبارة عن فشلاً عالمياً حقيقياً
The WHO is funded to monitor epidemics, but not to do these things I talked about.
تم تأسيس منظمة الصحة لمراقبة الأوبئة، و ليس للقيام بهذه الأشياء التي تحدثت عنها.
Now, in the movies it's quite different.
لكن، في الأفلام يبدو الأمر مختلفاً تماماً.
There's a group of handsome epidemiologists ready to go,
هناك مجموعة من علماء الأوبئة الوسيمين مستعدين للذهاب،
they move in, they save the day, but that's just pure Hollywood.
أنهم يتحركون، يقومون بإنقاذ الناس، ولكن هذا مجرد تمثيل.
The failure to prepare could allow the next epidemic
الفشل في الإعداد قد يسمح للوباء القادم
to be dramatically more devastating than Ebola
أن يكون أكثر تدميراً من الإيبولا
Let's look at the progression of Ebola over this year.
دعونا ننظر في تطور إيبولا خلال هذا العام.
About 10,000 people died,
قتل نحو 10،000 شخص،
and nearly all were in the three West African countries.
وكان معظمهم ينتمون الى البلدان الثلاثة الواقعة في غرب افريقيا.
There's three reasons why it didn't spread more.
هناك ثلاثة أسباب حالت دون إنتشار الوباء أكثر من ذلك.
The first is that there was a lot of heroic work by the health workers.
السبب الأول راجع الى العمل البطولي الذي قام به العاملين في مجال الصحة.
They found the people and they prevented more infections.
فهم يعالجون الناس ويمنعون المزيد من حالات الإصابة.
The second is the nature of the virus.
والثاني هو طبيعة الفيروس.
Ebola does not spread through the air.
إيبولا لا ينتشر عن طريق الهواء.
And by the time you're contagious,
فعندما يصل المرض الى مرحلة العدوى،
most people are so sick that they're bedridden.
يكون معظم المصابين طريحي الفراش.
Third, it didn't get into many urban areas.
ثالثا، لم يدخل الوباء الى كثير من المناطق الحضرية.
And that was just luck.
وكان ذلك مجرد حظ.
If it had gotten into a lot more urban areas,
لو دخل الى المناطق الحضرية،
the case numbers would have been much larger.
لكانت الأرقام أكبر من ذلك بكثير.
So next time, we might not be so lucky.
لذا في المرة القادمة، قد لن نكون محظوظين جدا.
You can have a virus where people feel well enough while they're infectious
يمكن أن يكون الفرد مصاباً بـفيروس معدٍ لكنه يشعر بحالة جيدة تمكنه
that they get on a plane or they go to a market.
من ركوب الطائرة أو الذهاب إلى السوق.
The source of the virus could be a natural epidemic like Ebola,
مصدر الفيروس يمكن أن يكون من الأوبئة الطبيعية مثل الإيبولا،
or it could be bioterrorism.
أويمكن أن يكون إرهاباً بيولوجياً.
So there are things that would literally make things a thousand times worse.
هناك أشياء يمكنها جعل الوضع أسوأ من ذلك بكثير.
In fact, let's look at a model of a virus spread through the air,
في الواقع، دعونا ننظر إلى نموذج لإنتشار فيروس عن طريق الهواء،
like the Spanish Flu back in 1918.
مثل الانفلونزا الاسبانية التي ظهرت في عام 1918.
So here's what would happen:
هذا ما يمكنه أن يحدث.
It would spread throughout the world very, very quickly.
يمكنها الإنتشار في جميع أنحاء العالم بسرعة كبيرة جداً.
And you can see over 30 million people died from that epidemic.
ويمكنكم رؤية أكثر من 30 مليون هلك من هذا الوباء.
So this is a serious problem.
لذلك فهذه مشكلة خطيرة.
We should be concerned.
علينا الإهتمام بالأمر.
But in fact, we can build a really good response system.
لكن في الواقع، يمكننا بناء نظام استجابة جيد للغاية.
We have the benefits of all the science and technology that we talk about here.
لدينا مزايا كل العلوم والتكنولوجيا التي تحدثنا عنها.
We've got cell phones
لدينا الهواتف المحمولة
to get information from the public and get information out to them.
للحصول على المعلومات من العامة ولإيصالها إليهم.
We have satellite maps where we can see where people are and where they're moving.
لدينا خرائط الأقمار الصناعية التي تمكننا من رؤية مكان تواجد الناس وكذك وجهتهم.
We have advances in biology
لدينا هذا التقدم في علم الأحياء
that should dramatically change the turnaround time to look at a pathogen
الذي ينبغي أن يُحدِث تغييراً هائلاً في المدة اللازمة للتعامل مع الفيروس
and be able to make drugs and vaccines that fit for that pathogen.
ونكون قادرين على صنع الأدوية واللقاحات المناسبة لهذا الفيروس.
So we can have tools,
لذا فإننا نمتلك أدوات،
but those tools need to be put into an overall global health system.
ولكن هذه الأدوات تحتاج إلى أن تُدمج في النظام الصحي العالمي.
And we need preparedness.
ونحتاج إلى التأهب.
The best lessons, I think, on how to get prepared
أعتقد أن أفضل الدروس لكيفية الإستعداد
are again, what we do for war.
هو مجدداً، ما الذي نقوم به للحرب.
For soldiers, we have full-time, waiting to go.
لدينا جنود مستعدين للإنطلاق في أي لحظة.
We have reserves that can scale us up to large numbers.
لدينا إحتياطيات يكفي لأعدادا كبيرة من الناس.
NATO has a mobile unit that can deploy very rapidly.
لدى حلف شمال الاطلسي وحدة متنقلة يمكن نشرها بسرعة كبيرة.
NATO does a lot of war games to check, are people well trained?
يقوم الناتو بـالكثير من المناورات الحربية للتحقق ما إذا كان جنودهم مدربين جيداً؟
Do they understand about fuel and logistics
هل يفهمون عن الوقود والخدمات اللوجستية
and the same radio frequencies?
ونفس ترددات الراديو؟
So they are absolutely ready to go.
لذلك هم على إستعداد دوماً للإنطلاق.
So those are the kinds of things we need to deal with an epidemic.
كانت تلك بعض الأشياء التي نحتاجهـا للتعامل مع الأوبئة.
What are the key pieces?
ما هي القطع الأساسية؟
First, we need strong health systems in poor countries.
أولا، نحن بحاجة لأنظمة صحية قوية في البلدان الفقيرة.
That's where mothers can give birth safely,
تمكّن الأمهات من الولادة بأمان،
kids can get all their vaccines.
والأطفال من الحصول على جميع اللقاحات.
But, also where we'll see the outbreak very early on.
وتمكن أيضاً من كشف بداية إنتشار الوباء في وقت مبكر.
We need a medical reserve corps:
نحن بحاجة إلى طاقم طبي دائم
lots of people who've got the training and background
الكثير من الناس المدربين وذوي تجربة
who are ready to go, with the expertise.
يكونوا على إستعداد للإنطلاق.
And then we need to pair those medical people with the military.
نحن بحاجة إلى مصاحبة هذا الطاقم الطبي بـالجيش.
taking advantage of the military's ability to move fast, do logistics
قصد الاستفادة من قدرة الجيش على التحرك بسرعة والعمل
and secure areas.
وتأمين المناطق.
We need to do simulations,
يتعين علينا القيام بمحاكاة،
germ games, not war games, so that we see where the holes are.
ألعاب جرثومية، وليس ألعاب حربية، حتى يتسنى لنا رؤية مكامن الضعف.
The last time a germ game was done in the United States
اخر مرة تم القيام بألعاب جرثومية في الولايات المتحدة
was back in 2001, and it didn't go so well.
كان عام 2001، ولم يكن كما يجب.
So far the score is germs: 1, people: 0.
حتى الآن النتيجة هي الجراثيم: 1، والناس: 0.
Finally, we need lots of advanced R&amp;D in areas of vaccines and diagnostics.
وأخيراً، نحن بحاجة إلى البحث المعمق في مجالات اللقاحات ووسائل التشخيص.
There are some big breakthroughs, like the Adeno-associated virus,
هناك بعض الاكتشافات العظيمة، مثل فيروس الغدة المرتبطة،
that could work very, very quickly.
الذي كان يمكن أن ينتشر بسرعة شديدة.
Now I don't have an exact budget for what this would cost,
الآن، لا أعلم كم سيكلف هذا من ميزانية تحديداً،
but I'm quite sure it's very modest compared to the potential harm.
ولكن أنا متأكد من أنها ضئيلة جداً بالمقارنة مع الأضرار المحتملة.
The World Bank estimates that if we have a worldwide flu epidemic,
يقدر البنك الدولي أنه إذا كان لدينا وباء إنفلونزا في جميع أنحاء العالم،
global wealth will go down by over three trillion dollars
فإن الثروة العالمية ستنخفض بأكثر من ثلاثة تريليونات دولار
and we'd have millions and millions of deaths.
وسيكون لدينا الملايين والملايين من الوفيات.
These investments offer significant benefits
ستوفر هذه الاستثمارات فوائد كبيرة
beyond just being ready for the epidemic.
أبعد من مجرد كونها مستعدة لمجابهة الوباء.
The primary healthcare, the R&amp;D,
الرعاية الصحية الأولية، والبحث المعمق،
those things would reduce global health equity
هذه الأمور ستقلل من التفاوت في مجال الصحة العالمي
and make the world more just as well as more safe.
وستجعل العالم أكثر عدلاً وكذلك أكثر أماناً.
So I think this should absolutely be a priority.
لذلك أعتقد أن هذا يجب أن يكون أولوية.
There's no need to panic.
ليس هناك حاجة للذعر.
We don't have to hoard cans of spaghetti or go down into the basement.
ليس علينا إكتناز علب السباغيتي أو الاحتماء في الطابق السفلي.
But we need to get going, because time is not on our side.
لكننا بحاجة للعمل، لأن الوقت ليس في صالحنا.
In fact, if there's one positive thing that can come out of the Ebola epidemic,
في الواقع، هناك شيء إيجابي واحد يمكن أن يستخلص من وباء إيبولا،
it's that it can serve as an early warning, a wake-up call, to get ready.
أنه يمكن أن يكون بمثابة الإنذار المبكر، أو دعوة للاستيقاظ، للإستعداد.
If we start now, we can be ready for the next epidemic.
إذا بدأنا الآن، فيمكننا أن نكون على أهبة الإستعداد للوباء القادم.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)